בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ז. Daf Zayin.
We pick up on the middle of ו עמוד ב. Vav amud
bet. The גמרא's Gemara in the middle of a discussion. The משנה
Mishnah was discussing the issue of who pays for the wall. The
first ארבע אמות arba amot is shared. Afterwards, you can't get your
neighbor to pay for a wall except if he built a parallel
wall and shows that he wants it, then you join in in
the payment of the wall. So, as has been pointed out to
me many times since we started this a few days ago, building
a wall and trying to get your—again, with your neighbor's property and
trying to get him to pay for it—and who says the דף
daf isn't relevant? Okay, anyway, so alright, so anyway, but now the
גמרא Gemara a little bit turns back to the basic some of
the questions about the היזק ראיה hezek reiyah issue and when you
can compel somebody to build the base wall, even before we get
to talk about higher than normal. So let's take a look. אמר
רב נחמן,
Amar Rav
Nachman, it is the second wide line on ו עמוד ב. Vav
amud bet. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel,
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, גג
הסמוך לחצר חבירו עושה לו מעקה גבוה ארבע אמות. Gag hasamuch lachatzar
chaveiro, ose lo maakeh gavoha arba amot. If you have—we had mentioned
this earlier—if you have a roof that overlooks your friend's yard, so
you have to make a wall around your roof so you can't
look into your friend's yard. Your friend making the wall won't do
him any good; you can still look in. So you have to
make a wall around your roof. Again, we're bracketing questions about the
normal מצוה mitzvah of מעקה maakeh to prevent somebody from falling off;
this is specifically a wall for the purposes of privacy. Okay,
אבל בין גג לגג לא, aval bein gag legag lo, but if
you have two
neighboring rooftops, you don't have to. And it could be that there's
a gap between the buildings; it could even be it's continuous.
You know, you can go in the Old City, you can sort
of get to a place, get on top of the buildings, and
there's a wide expanse of concrete and it looks like it's just
basically like a floor, you know, but it's really all the rooftops
of all the buildings combined. So anyway, so in that case you
do, because that would sort of like be a yard adjoining a
yard, and you
have—I'm sorry, you don't, excuse me. And the question is, why don't
you? Why isn't it—hold on, let me get this right—yeah, אבל בין
גג לגג לא, aval bein gag legag lo, right. So why isn't
that just like two neighboring yards? So he says you don't have
to. רב נחמן דידיה, Rav Nachman didey, that's רב נחמן Rav Nachman
in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, but רב נחמן Rav Nachman himself
says, אמר אינו זקוק לארבע אמות אבל זקוק למחיצה עשרה. amar eino
zakuk l'arba amot aval zakuk limchitzah asarah. For this case about the
adjoining rooftops, it might be you don't need a wall of ארבע
אמות, arba amot, so it's not about היזק ראיה, hezek reiyah, but
you do need a עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim wall, which is like
about two and a half
feet maybe?
What? No, it's not a מעקה; maakeh; let's keep on looking. Because
again, these anyway would be rooftops that are adjoining, so it's between
the rooftops; it's not between the rooftop and the edge of the
building. Okay, so let's see what that's about.
So למאי? lemai? So compared to a ארבע אמות arba amot which
is about six feet, this is about half the height or a
little less, two and a half feet or so. So למאי, lemai,
for what purpose does—what good does this do? אי להיזק ראיה ארבע
אמות בעינן. iy l'hezek reiyah, arba amot beinan. If he's saying there's
a concern over joining rooftops of היזק ראיה, hezek reiyah, you should
need four. Now, why would there not be a concern? What's שמואל's
Shmuel position? So, presumably there's not a concern that since the rooftops
are used only occasionally, then it's not considered a serious היזק hezek
to prevent me from doing private things on my rooftop, because, you
know, I don't do it so much; it's a rare type of
a use I have anyway. And maybe if I, you know, and
if I'm there, I could see if you're using it or not.
It's not like, you know, a neighboring yard where I expect you
to come out of your house any moment and be in your
yard. So, maybe the assumption here is even if it does constrain
you, it's not so much; it's not constraining like a lot of
activity, and that maybe there's more ways to sort of to be
careful. So, it's not clear. But that's presumably שמואל's Shmuel position, that
there's no היזק ראיה hezek reiyah concern. But what's רב נחמן's Rav
Nachman position? If רב נחמן Rav Nachman thinks there is היזק ראיה,
hezek reiyah, then עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim should not be enough; you
should need
ארבע אמות. arba amot. אי לנצולי עליו כגנב, iy lenitzolei alav keganav,
maybe you don't want somebody climbing on your rooftop—you know, it's a
trespassing
issue—okay, and, you know, if you don't have some type of a
divider and somebody's on your rooftop, they'll say, 'I didn't realize I
was on your rooftop, you know, I thought this was just a
continuation of mine.' This especially makes sense if the rooftops are all
contiguous, you know, and you can't even see the dividing line from
below; it's literally, you know, just
one continuous piece of concrete or whatever. So then, if it's to
create a dividing line that the person shouldn't trespass,
so the גמרא Gemara says במיצרא בעלמא סגי. bemitzra b'alma sagi.
So just have like small pegs, right? You don't need עשרה טפחים.
asarah tefachim. אי לגדיים
ורטושין—now, iy legidayim u'rtushin if you're afraid about goats
and little baby sheep and goats... now, how they got to the
rooftop is pretty surprising, you know, but again, I mean, I think
if we're thinking about our contemporary... buildings, it doesn't make any sense,
unless who knows, maybe you've got you got a little garden up
on your rooftop and you keep your baby goat up at your
garden on your rooftop. But again if you think about, I don't
know,
have people been at this this thing I'm describing in the old
city where you can get on top of all the buildings and
you have... so who knows, maybe it is possible to have goats
running around there.
And they say they used the rooftops for first of all they
slept there all summer. They dried fruit on the top. So it
was a very used... Right. It wasn't necessarily such a big leap.
Big leap, aha. Large projects on the roof in the Arabic village,
then it's a whole thing.
It's right. It's like its own...
Protected yard.
Right, it's like a huge yard essentially, right. So presumably maybe you
have goats or whatever, so you need so you need something that's
a little bit higher. So the גמרא Gemara says בכדי שלא יזדקר
בבת ראש סגי, bechdei shelo yizdaker bevat rosh sagi, it's enough that
they can't sort of like just put their heads through, which is
more like, you know, which is a few טפחים tefachim but it's
not ten טפחים. tefachim. Might only be three טפחים tefachim is enough,
from other גמרות Gemaras it sounds like. So the גמרא Gemara says
so what's this ten טפחים? tefachim? So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם
לא נתפס עליו כגנב, leolam lo nitfas alav k'ganav, fine, it's a
property line to prevent trespassing. So why isn't like some pegs enough?
דמצי מצי משתמיט ליה, dematzei matzei mishtamit lei, but if it's just
low pegs you can sort of like excuse it say... now some
have a question whether you have this גרסא girsa in the middle.
אמרי מציורי קא מציורינא, amrei mitzurei ka mitzureina, like I was just
like pushed up against the edge, you know it was tiny little
pegs, I didn't see where I was going, I stepped over them.
It's, you know, somebody could come up with an excuse why they
weren't paying attention to the pegs, okay? מחיצת עשרה לא מצי משתמיט
ליה, mechitzas asara lo matzei mishtamit lei,
but with a מחיצה mechitza ten טפחים tefachim they can't say I
didn't realize that this was your property. Fine. Anyway what's more interesting,
I mean it is interesting that we have this new position of
ten טפחים tefachim as a property line,
but what do you call it, but also what's actually strange is
that until now, you know, the discussion always was can you force
your neighbor to participate. So here if you want to just create
a little bit of a fence to prevent trespassing, be my guest,
who's stopping you? Presumably the point is that I can say if
we have these adjoining rooftops, we're going to build a fence to
prevent trespassing and you have to chip in even though you don't
want to. So that becomes interesting. The same way you have an
obligation to ensure that you don't do היזק ראייה hezek reiya to
your friend and you participate in the wall, you have an obligation
to sort of like protect each other from this trespassing. Like we
saw that before, you know, there are these obligations that are sort
of because you're neighbors or because you're sharing a courtyard or because
you're in all in the same town that you can force everybody
to participate because it's seen as either for the common good or
you have a responsibility not to cause damage. I mean the common
good would be the case of like, you know, we all have
to pay for the wall of the city, of the town. we
all have to pay for a wall around our courtyard, okay, but
so that's like you're trying to do a common good and the
possible damage comes from the outside. But here again what's interesting is
another damage that you could be causing me is the potential that
you might step into my yard, that it's a trespass concern and
you would have to participate in it. So that's one thing. The
other thing is is the idea that these rooftops are not like
two joining yards. That two joining yards because there's a lot of,
you know, they're regular use, there's היזק ראייה. hezek reiya. A rooftop
overlooking a yard because the guy in the yard has regular use
and that's compromising it, it's היזק ראייה. hezek reiya. Two adjoining rooftops,
right, where each has only rare use or uncommon, that even though
the reality is I might be wanting to have a picnic, you
know like a party with my friends when you're having one with
your friends and we can't be as comfortable if people are looking
at one another, since it's rarer that's not considered to be היזק
ראייה. hezek reiya.
Yes Dave? One interesting aspect of this is that at least if
I'm understanding correctly is that by the גג gag versus the חצר,
chatzer, the גג, gag, the owner of the גג gag has to
do the whole thing himself, right?
If you want to create a privacy fence, yes.
But no no but
it's the...
Oh yes the גג gag overlooking a חצר, chatzer, that is correct,
that is correct.
So my sense is that unlike a חצר chatzer versus a חצר
chatzer where somehow I guess...
Right, because a חצר chatzer to a חצר chatzer we're both potentially
injuring each other. Here this guy is there's only one מזיק.
mazik. It's really about... it's really about protecting the other rather than...
Exactly, when you're dealing with היזק ראייה, hezek reiya, right. But as
opposed to cases of common good, which we'll get to, right. But
here it's only one person who's the damager and one the damagee
with a גג gag and a חצר. chatzer. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay מיתיבי, Meitivei, they asked on this. אם היה חצרו למעלה מגגו
של חברו, im haya chatzero lemala migago shel chavero, if your yard
was higher than your friend's rooftop. You could have that too, I
mean it's unusual but you could have it. So אין נזקקין לו.
ein nizkakin lo. So we do not demand that a wall be
built. Now here you are in the yard and you're regularly overlooking
this guy's rooftop, so the presence of your ראייה reiya is much
more constant, okay, but nevertheless presumably the חצר chatzer because it has
less use in the חצר, chatzer, it's rarer to be... I'm not
the חצר, chatzer, the גג gag because its roof is... I mean
not the חצר, chatzer, the גג, gag, because its roof is rarer
than it's not so much היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah that there's a
חצר chatzer above. Okay, because it's so that seems to be it:
to compromise the use of a roof is not so much היזק
ראיה. hezek re'iyah. Okay, so אין לו עסק עמו. ein lo esek
imo. You don't, you don't, you know, you cannot, you know, sort
of like make any demands from him. So the Gemara says: מאי
לאו אין לו עסק עמו כלל, mai lav ein lo esek imo
klal, you know, if the person at the bottom wants, you know,
wants you with the yard above to make a wall, it must
mean that he can't ask for anything, even a wall for that's
to prevent trespass. So that's a proof against Rav Nachman. So the
Gemara says: לא אין לו עסק עמו בארבע אמות. lo ein lo
esek imo b'arba amot. You cannot sort of meet his demands to
make a four-amah wall because, you know, again, his yard is higher
than your roof, so it's only compromising your use of a roof,
which is not a good enough היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah claim, אבל
עסק יש לו במחיצה של עשרה, aval esek yesh lo b'mechitzah shel
asarah, you can, you would, you would agree to a demand for
a smaller wall for trespass concerns. I don't understand, once something's not
at a common level, once they're at different levels, I don't understand
why you need something to prevent trespass, right? At the very fact
that they're at different, even if it's like a gradual slope, I
would imagine, you know,
even a gradual slope counts as an עירוב.
eiruv. Yeah, it's not exactly clear to me how, why, I mean,
I guess if it's really gradual and you don't notice it. But
anyway, it's not exactly clear to me once they're at different levels
why you need, like why this was a question to begin with.
Why you would need something for trespass?
I guess it's a jump of something's. I mean if the jump
is less than, than עשרה טפחים, asarah tefachim, maybe you need it,
right?
Right. You know, imagine if you excavate a room out of a
hill. Right. So you know, and now you have a roof on
that hill that is, you know, abuts...
Right. I guess if it's, you're right, if it's gradual enough or
maybe not high enough, then there could still be the point like
I could go into your rooftop without noticing what I'm doing. So
you could still demand it. Anyway, the Gemara says the basic point
here is more about the what do you call it, is about
the היזק ראיה. hezek re'iyah. We're not dealing with the מחיצה של
עשרה. mechitzah shel asarah. Okay. Yes.
You know, Rashi says unlike if you would just like mark it
with those little pegs, you know, you could just sort of ignore
it. Rashi says for some reason it's a little bit more intentional
than that. He says like, oh I just came here because I
lost my
pig and I came in.
Right. So it's a little bit more,
you mean it's not accidental trespass. Yeah. So the Gemara says נתפס
עליו כגנב. nitpas alav k'ganav. So that sounds, so basically it's like
for like an intentional trespass. Right. And then your claim, oh I
wasn't paying attention, but why were you actually trespassing? You know, it
sounds like that could be intentional. Okay. איתמר. itmar. It was said.
שתי חצירות זו למעלה מזו. shtei chatzerot zo l'malah mi'zo. Now back
to two yards, one higher than another. Okay. So there is a
היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah to compromise the use of my yard, but
the guy at the top isn't being damaged because, you know, he
can't be, or much less likely he's being damaged. It's much harder
to see what's going on at the top. The guy at the
bottom is. Okay. So it's much worse than, again, the case about
a roof overlooking a yard. I'm at the bottom. I've got the
yard. I have this common use I want to do. And you
are at the top and might be regularly looking into me. Okay.
So let's take a look. שתי חצירות זו למעלה מזו. shtei chatzerot
zo l'malah mi'zo. Where are we? איתמר. itmar. Lost my place. שתי
חצירות זו למעלה מזו. shtei chatzerot zo l'malah mi'zo. אמר רב הונא.
amar Rav Huna. תחתון בונה מכנגדו ועולה. tachton boneh miknegdo v'oleh. ועליון
בונה מכנגדו
ועולה. v'elyon boneh miknegdo v'oleh. So the bottom one has to build
up to his height and the top one has to continue building
to his height. So I have to tell you I don't really
fully understand the logic here. I mean just the sort of physical
layout.
But if you imagine here are two courtyards, right here's my house
and here's your house, and this is my yard, that's your yard,
so I'm overlooking you. So I'm going to have to build a
wall, right? Now you, so apparently, so if I build the wall,
I can't see you, and then presumably you also can't see me.
Okay. So you would think that the, this would be the only
wall we would need and this would be the best wall. Now
and maybe I should participate because maybe it's still somewhat possible for
me to see you. It's unclear. Okay. But this would be the
only wall we're talking about. It sounds like from what the Gemara
saying is we build a wall starting here till I get to
your property line, and this is I have to pay, if ראובן
Reuven is down here and שמעון Shimon is here, so I have
to pay for all of this. And then you go ahead and
you pay for this. So I don't understand that, which is why
is this wall needed? Just build it over to...
Unless... I don't know, maybe the ArtScroll has a picture or something
that helps understand this. But I wasn't really able to understand why
not to just build it all on שמעון's Shimon property. It could
be that the, what do you call it, it could be that
the slope is more gradual, right? It could be, hold on, sorry.
Oh I don't even know what I'm doing here. Forget this. Okay.
It could be the slope is more gradual, right? If the slope
is more gradual like that. Okay. But I still don't get it.
I mean, I guess if my yard ends here, then just build
a wall here. If my yard ends, oh maybe that's it. Maybe
this is it. Maybe my yard, שמעון's Shimon yard ends here. This
is the property line. So we're going to build... on the property
line and we're going, that makes sense, and we're going to build
it on the property line, and then we have to build, but
we have to build a wall that goes all the way up.
So in this case, you build that, you know, ראובן Reuven participates
up to here and we jointly do it from there up, which
explain, that would explain why not to just to build at the
higher elevation or something like this. Right, is that the picture that,
does Artscroll have a picture? Do they describe it anyway?
I just saw this picture.
Does it look like this?
Yeah, basically. Except that it assumes that
it's, no, the ש"ס Shas Artscroll picture does not explain why you
need the bottom wall. If it was a drop, you wouldn't need
the bottom wall, you should build it all in שמעון Shimon's property.
It doesn't imply that there's a, there's a gradual slope. Our משנה
Mishna tells us that, by the first משנה Mishna tells us that
you have to build it between the property.
Between the property.
Right, so, so שמעון Shimon has the right to say that no
ראובן, Reuven, I don't want to build it all on my property.
So as a result, ראובן Reuven needs to build, if you imagine
instead of a slope, a cliff, right, at the property line.
Yes, but the, yes, I thought about that. Whose property is it
being built on? But if it's like this, so then שמעון Shimon
can say I don't want it on mine, but ראובן Reuven can
say I don't want it on mine. No, no, no. And if
you build it like this, then it's all going to be on
ראובן Reuven because then you're going to continue it like that.
No, but if that is the property line, right, if that's the
property line where the cliff is, so ראובן Reuven has to build
the support for the half that will be on his side of
the property line beneath. So that when it gets to the property,
gets to the top level,
the שמעון Shimon's level,
then you can have half on, on the wall that's being supported
by ראובן. Reuven.
Oh, you mean once you get here, you're going to build it
like this? Correct. Maybe. So maybe that's it. Maybe to allow for
it to be, I don't know, could be. Okay, I think the
slope case also answers it though, if the property line is lower,
but I'm at the, but ultimately, you know, I'm going to be
partly at a higher elevation. Anyway, so let's take a look at
the different opinions in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. תחתון בונה מכנגדו ועולה
והעליון בונה מכנגדו ועולה. Tachton boneh mikenegdo ve'oleh veh'elyon boneh mikenegdo ve'oleh.
The bottom one builds, you know, his half and the top one
builds his half. רב חסדא אמר עליון מסייע מלמטה ובונה. Rav Chisda
amar elyon mesayeya milimata uboneh.
No, the bottom guy has to also pay for half of the
wall below, the top guy has to pay for half of the
wall below, because that's also necessary for his wall to be built
is to get the below part built as well. So let's just
do my example because I just think whatever, I don't know if
it's correct or not but I think it makes a little bit
more sense to see what's going on. If this is the property
line, you're going to need a wall like this at the property
line level. So the question is who pays for this part? You
could say I pay for this part because I also can't see
into you. But the point is since you, in order to protect
yourself, need the bottom part as well in order to get this
high, then you have to participate in the building of the bottom
part as well. That's the, that's the second opinion. Okay.
Okay. רב חסדא Rav Chisda fine. תניא כוותיה דרב חסדא. Tanyah kevata
de Rav Chisda. We taught like רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. שתי חצירות,
Shteih chatzeirot, זו למעלה מזו. zo lemala mizo. Two courtyards, one higher
than the other. זו למעלה מזו. zo lemala mizo. לא יאמר העליון
הריני בונה מכנגדי ועולה. lo yomar ha'elyon hareni boneh mikenegdi ve'oleh.
I'm only going to build my top half. אלא מסייע מלמטה ובונה.
ela mesayeya milimata uboneh. He has to also participate in the building
of the bottom half. ואם היתה חצר למעלה מגגו של חבירו. veim
hayetah hatzeir lemala migago shel chaveiro. This is the end of the
ברייתא Braita that we, this end of the ברייתא Braita we quoted
earlier. If the yard is higher than the, than the roof, אינו
זקוק לו, eino zakuk lo, then he has no need to build
a wall because, you know, the roof, again, compromising the use of
the roof is not seen as a major היזק ראייה hezek reiyah
type of a concern. Okay. ההוא בי תרי דהוו דיירי. hahu bei
trei dahavu dayarei.
Two people were, you know, what do you call it, were living
in one house, one above and one below. Okay, that gets us
back to issues we had like, you know, whatever, at the end
of בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. חד הוה דייר עלי וחד הוה דייר
תתאי. chad hava dayar elai vechad hava dayar tata'ei. One was living
above and one was living below. אתבר תתאי itvar tata'ei or sometimes
אתבס תתאי. itvas tata'ei. And the bottom building not broke but somehow
like רש"י Rashi says like the wall sank a little. So basically,
you now have the bottom sill, the ceiling of the bottom guy
dropped. Like the wall somehow sank or the foundation sank and the
bottom guy now has a house that's much, has very little height
to it, but the top guy is totally happy. His part is
totally as it used to be. Okay. Cathedral ceiling. Exactly.
Well, no, no, no, it's not the way רש"י Rashi explained it,
it's not that the roof moved relative to the wall, the whole
wall sort of sunk, sunk into the ground. So effectively the roof
came down, the top guy's thing looks like it always looked, but
the bottom guy's has now, yep, okay. Right. אתבר. itva. So אמר
תתאי לעילאי. amar tata'ei le'ilai. So the bottom guy said to the
top guy, תו נבנייה. tav nibnyei. Come let's rebuild this bottom part
of the building. And maybe he's offering to do it all on
his own dime. Okay. אמר ליה אנא שפיר קא דיירנא. amar lei
ana shappir kadiyerna. So he said, I'm happy, what do you mean
come build it, I don't need to. Okay.
So, אמר ליה. amar lei. So at first he was saying let's
jointly rebuild it. And the guy says, what do you mean, I
don't have any need to rebuild the bottom. אמר ליה, amar lei,
אשתרי אנא. ishtarei ana. אמר ליה Amar Lei אסתרי אנא ואבניה, istari
ana v'evneiah, I will pay for the construction, I want to rebuild
the whole building or whatever to get the bottom, you know, livable,
and I will pay for the whole construction. אמר ליה Amar Lei
ליכא דוכתא למיתב בה. leika duchtei l'meitav bei. No, I refuse. I
don't want to get kicked out of my house for six months
while it's being rebuilt. אמר ליה Amar Lei אנא אוגר לך דוכתא.
ana ogeir lach duchtei. I'll rent you a place, okay? Just let
me knock this down and rebuild it. אמר ליה לא טרחנא. Amar
lei lo tarchna, Nah, I don't want the effort. I like it
here. לא קא מדדר ליה. lo kamidarda lei. So the guy says,
what do you mean? But I can't live in this bottom part.
So he said, שופא כריסך ואעול ושופא כריסך ואפוק, shufa kreichach v'aeul
v'shufa kreichach v'afok, you know, sort of squirm in on your stomach
and get in, and squirm in on your stomach and get out.
It's not my problem. You have a low ceiling? Well live with
it. So you'll eat lying down or something. You know?
All right. So meaning, it's not my problem. You can't force me
out of my house just because you now don't have a place
to live. אמר רב חמא, Amar Rav Chama, so Rav Chama
said, בדינא קא מעכב. b'dina kamiaikeiv. Actually, that is completely legitimate. You
on top have no responsibility
to accommodate the guy below. It's a little נבך, nebech, but he
can't force you to leave your, you know, what do you call
it, you know, your domicile if you don't want to. והני מילי
דלא מטו כשורי למטה מעשרה. v'hanei milei d'lo matu kashurei l'mata m'asara.
But it's interesting, at a certain point we do say you do
have to, you know, if it's really completely uninhabitable, you do, you
know, he can ask you to put you up somewhere else until
he can rebuild it. Because when can he not do that? When
the ceiling beams are not within ten טפחים. tefachim. אבל מטו כשורי
למטה מעשרה. aval matu kashurei l'mata m'asara. If it's within ten טפחים,
tefachim, it's very interesting, it's not by chance, this is the exact
minimum height of a סוכה, sukkah, okay? That it's considered to be
that less than ten טפחים, tefachim, now ten טפחים tefachim is only
about
30-36 inches. So it's not so livable, like even if it's like
ten טפחים tefachim and I'm not tall, right?
But that's the real application of שופא כריסך. shufa kreichach.
I know, I guess you could maybe everybody you could sit down
in the place, you could lie down in the place, just don't
stand up in it. Okay anyway, in that case, okay, but in
that place it's really not inhabitable. והני מילי... v'hanei milei... אבל מטו
כשורי למטה מעשרה מצי אמר ליה למטה מעשרה רשותי דידי הוא. aval
matu kashurei l'mata m'asara matzi amar lei l'mata m'asara reshusi didi hu.
Now here's the explanation. It's not just I have no place to
live and it's really uninhabitable. It's you are now encroaching into my
territory, okay? Because now you are within ten טפחים, tefachim, and within
ten טפחים tefachim is considered to be like the natural airspace of
the ground. If I have rights to the ground, right, like the
height of a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim is ten טפחים, tefachim, and
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid goes even higher, but ten טפחים tefachim
is considered to be the immediate airspace of a location. So if
you're within ten טפחים, tefachim, it's now I could sort of say,
it's like you're living in the bottom, at the bottom level. That's
my level now. So it's actually the Gemara frames it not so
much because it's uninhabitable, but because now I really can force you
out, because I could say you're living in my space. Okay.
Could he force the other guy to build, to do the whole
construction in that situation?
That's what I was wondering that. Like once he's in, once he
is, you know, maybe you can force or can you just force
him to pay the amount of the construction that would require to
go ten טפחים tefachim but not higher, right? That at least is
I think a good question. Or this is just saying that that
at least, that enough gives you the right to get him to
live somewhere else until you get it done, right? But how much
does that make him a partner to the construction? It's a good
question. Yeah, I was wondering the same thing. I haven't looked it
up. אבל מטו כשורי למטה מעשרה מצי אמר ליה למטה מעשרה רשותי
דידי הוא ולא משעביד לך. aval matu kashurei l'mata m'asara matzi amar
lei l'mata m'asara reshusi didi hu v'lo misha'abid lach. You know, it
is not, you don't have rights to the space below ten. You're
now in my space. Okay. And then again you can definitely get
something, you can definitely get it built. How much you can make
him pay for is an open question. והני מילי דלא אתנו בהדי
הדדי. v'hanei milei d'lo asnu bahadi hadadi. Now that's all if when
they originally split the house, רשי Rashi says probably we're talking about
brothers who inherited a house and they split it, they didn't make
any stipulations. אבל אתנו בהדי הדדי, aval asnu bahadi hadadi, but if
they made any stipulations, if they said, hey look, if there's ever
a time that because of one of us we need to rebuild
a house, then we're going to agree to allow the house to
get rebuilt and we'll, you know, make our accommodations, etc. In that
case, סתרו ובנו, sastro u'banu, then they can knock it down and
rebuild it. Not such a big חידוש, chiddush, they made a stipulation.
וכי אתנו בהדי הדדי עד כמה. v'ki asnu bahadi hadadi ad kama.
Now, if they did make a stipulation, but let's say they didn't
say what defines something as needing to be fixed, okay? They made
a stipulation, if ever it sinks or needs to be fixed or
whatever, then we will go ahead knock it down and rebuild it
and whoever's going to pay for it will pay for it. Okay,
but without stipulating what means needs to be fixed, what would be
the definition of how far would the ceiling have to drop? Okay.
וכי אתנו
בהדי הדדי עד כמה v'ki asnu bahadi hadadi ad kama אמרו רבנן
קמיה דרבא משמיה דמר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן דאמר משמיה דרב נחמן.
amru rabanan kamei d'Rava mishmei d'Mar Zutra breih d'Rav Nachman d'amar mishmei
d'Rav Nachman. So that's a long attribution. כאותה ששנינו k'osa sheshaninu רומו
כחצי ארכו
וכחצי רחבו, rumo k'chatzi archo v'chatzi rachvo, like that which we taught,
its height is like half its length and half its width. The
height of the משכן Mishkan basically, or רש״י Rashi says this is
generally that, if you basically contract to build a house, how high
are you supposed to make the ceilings if it hasn't been specified?
So it says we learn it out from the משכן, Mishkan, the
משכן Mishkan was
40 אמות amos by 20 אמות amos with the ceil- hold on
let me just check רש״י. Rashi. I'm sorry, not the משכן, Mishkan,
the מקדש. Mikdash.
Yeah, the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, it was 40 אמות amos by 20
אמות amos and 30 אמות amos high. Okay, so which basically means
that the ceilings were half the height of the combined width and
length. You got that? It was 40 by 20, that's 60, and
half. So basically the height of the ceilings is relative, this apparently
is the time where you don't have multi-story houses, so if you
have a huge, I mean we would think if you've got a
huge place with a big width and length, you might have two,
three stories in the house, right? But if you really are thinking
that fundamentally one story and you've got a huge place, so the
bigger the place, the higher you're going to want the ceilings in
order to חשוב chashuv a place. You don't want a big place
with low ceiling, right? So that's, so he said the same way
that's what we assume if you contract somebody to build a house
and you specified width and length and not ceiling height, that the
ceiling height is half of the combined width and length. So here
too if they didn't stipulate and it goes within that space, the,
you know, it sinks within that space, excuse me, if they did
stipulate that they would rebuild it but they didn't stipulate what were
the conditions, then it would be once the ceiling gets lower than
that height. Okay,
so רומו, rumo, its height, כחצי אורכו וכחצי רוחבו. k'chatzi orcho v'chatzi
rochvo. אמר ליה רבא לאו אמינא לכו, amar lei Rava lav amina
l'chu, so רבא Rava said to all these people who quoted this
in the name of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, he said to them,
didn't I tell you לא תתלו ביה בוקי סריקי ברב נחמן, lo
titlu bei bukei srikei b'Rav Nachman, don't attribute like these, you know,
like these, this is I don't know, it's an idiom but like
don't attribute all these empty ideas to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, don't,
you know, why are you attributing such silly points, silly ideas in
the name of רב נחמן? Rav Nachman? I don't believe רב נחמן
Rav Nachman ever said that.
Wasn't it רב נחמן's Rav Nachman son that-?
Yeah, I know, it was, right, it was exactly בריה דרב נחמן
משמיה דרב נחמן. breih d'Rav Nachman mishmei d'Rav Nachman. Yeah, that's impossible,
רב נחמן Rav Nachman never said anything so foolish. הכי אמר רב
נחמן, hachi amar Rav Nachman, this is what רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said, כדדיירי אינשי, k'd'daieri inshi, you know, it's one it's as normal
people live, I mean how would you estimate that, but you know,
whatever it may be, whatever the norm is that, you know, in
that place, 10 foot ceilings, whatever the norm is. It's, you know,
so it's not that what's habitable, it's the normal way in which
it is, because again here we made an explicit stipulation that once
there's a problem we could rebuild it. Okay, but so it doesn't
have to be uninhabitable but it has to be that it compromises
the normal types of living conditions. וכמה? v'chama? So now the גמרא
Gemara says great, what's that? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע כי
היכי דעיילי איסטורא דמחוזא והדר. amar Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua k'heichi
d'ayeli istura d'machuza v'hadar. Like somebody who is carrying in a,
like רש״י Rashi says like a big, like a long bundle of
sticks, he can walk into the house and he can like turn
around, he has good maneuverability. So again how long are the sticks?
Okay, I don't also understand the point of maneuverability because we're talking
about height, maneuverability has more to do with sort of, you know,
the width that you've got. But anyway somebody carrying in a big
bundle of sticks if they can make it into the house and
again are they carrying the bundle of sticks lengthwise, right? Or it
sounds like they're carrying it lengthwise which would be a funny way
to carry but maybe anyway, all right, so whatever that is, okay,
a certain type of a height that is that is not so
high that it's half the width and the length but also not
so low.
You know I wonder whether it could be that that you look
at the
essentially the narrowest, the diameter of the smallest, of the largest circle
you can create in it? That's the turning around, and then if
you turn that on its side, that diameter would end up being,
so you end up being a little bit less than half the
average of the-
yeah, but how long are the sticks? You're saying oh, you're saying
take a stick that would let you do a circle just, you
know, bare and then stand it up the other way.
That's, how does that fit with the רומו כחצי אורכו? rumo k'chatzi
orcho?
It would be, it would end up being right, it would end
up being half the smallest of the of whichever side is whichever
size of
your- right, right, right.
So you take the shorter, well so you take the width if
we say the way width means the shorter dimension, and then it
is half of the width. No no, and then it is the
width, it is the width, it is the width. So it's only
a slight variation on the half width half length version. That's an
interesting possibility, right, you're right. What does it matter that you can
turn around if we're talking about height? It's an interesting interpretation, yeah.
Not that you get different dimensions necessarily, it's the way of thinking,
in other words if you have a מקדש מעט Mikdash me'at in
the first place,
or you build
it with references, you
don't reference it, that's
what
you- right, right. But it's but it's also doesn't have to be
the ideal, it just has to be the norm. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, ההוא hahu But it's also it
doesn't have to be the idea, it just has to be the
norm. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ההוא גברא
דהוה בני אשישתא אחורי כווי דחבריה. Hahu gavra d'avei banya ashista achorei
kivei d'chavrei. This is a great story. Somebody built a house, which
is directly facing the windows of his neighbor's house. Now before we
learned that the wall, if you're building a wall, it has to
be four אמות amot away from your neighbor's house to let the
light in. But that was also a standard four אמות amot wall,
right? Here you're building a whole house opposite your neighbor's house and
so on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה
קא מאפלת עלי, Amar lei ka ma’afeilat alai, you are making it
dark for me. אמר ליה סכרנא לך הכא ובנינא לך כווי לעיל
משיטאי, Amar lei sacharna lach hacha v'vanyina lach kivei l'eila mishita'i, you
know what I'll do? I will agree to brick up your current
windows, because now they're blocked from the sunlight anyway, and I will
pay for the building of windows in your wall higher than where
my wall is. Okay, now of course, you know, it seems like
the only purpose of the windows is to let in light, not
to have a nice view or whatever it is, because you could
say like I don't care just about the light, I mean the
light, I don't know, would the light presumably be better if the—I
guess it depends because you're going to get the shadow of the
wall, right? If you've got your—here, and your window here, and this
is like your, you know whatever, this is like your living room,
right? So then you get some nice direct sunlight there. If the
window was up here, right, it would go further, right, but it
would not give you sunlight, you know, you wouldn't be right near
to where your window was. What?
It would just depend on the time of day and season.
Oh, it might depend on that too. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
is completely
oblivious—right, that's true. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is completely oblivious to
all those issues. Let's keep on going. Okay, so אמר ליה, Amar
Lei no you know what, it's fine, I'll just build windows for
you higher up in your wall. ובנינא לך כווי לעיל משיטאי. V'vanyina
lach kivei l'eila mishita'i.
אמר
ליה קא מרעית לה לאשישתא, Amar lei ka mareis lah l'ashista, if
you're going to knock in, you know, holes in the wall to
put in windows, that's going to damage the wall. אמר ליה סתרנא
לך לאשישתך עד דוכתא דכווי, Amar lei satarna lach l'ashitech ad duchtah
d'chivei,
you know what I'll do? I will knock down your wall from
here, my opposite wall was going over here, okay, so I'm going
to build windows above my wall. So says you're going to damage
this part of the wall by putting in knocking in a hole
and making a window. You know what I'll do? I will knock
down this entire part of the wall and rebuild it from this
point up, you know, and put the window here and rebuild it
from that point up. Okay, so so so it won't be damaged,
it'll be a new construction on the top. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so he said back to him,
סתרנא לך עד דוכתא דכווי, Satarna lach ad duchtah d'chivei, from the
roof to where we're going to put the windows, ובנינא לה ואבינא
לך כווי בבנינא לעילא משיטאי, u'vanyina lah v'avina lach kivei bevinyana l'eila
mishita'i,
and then I'll make—see, I will make the windows before you get
to my wall. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so you'll have a totally
new construction on the top. אמר ליה Amar lei, said back to
him, אשישתא מתתא עתיקא ומלעילא חדתא לא קיימא, Ashista mitata atika u'mil'eila
chadta lo kayma, a wall that the below is an old wall
and the top is a new wall is not as sturdy. אמר
ליה Amar lei he said fine, you know what I'll do? סתרנא
לה עד לארעא ובנינא לה ואבינא לך כווי בבנינא, Satarna lah ad
l'ara u'vanyina lah v'avina lach kivei bevinyana, I will knock down your
entire wall and rebuild it
and put the windows up higher up. אמר ליה Amar lei he
said to him, חד אשישתא חדתא בכולי ביתא עתיקא לא קיימא, Chad
ashista chadta bechuli beita atika lo kayma, one new wall and the
rest of the house is an old house, it won't do any
good. אמר ליה Amar lei he said to him, fine! סתרנא ליה
לכוליה ביתא, Satarna leh l'chulei beita, I will knock down your whole
house, ובנינא לך כווי בבנינא, u'vanyina lach kivei bevinyana, and I will
put in new windows. אמר ליה לית לי דוכתא למידר ביה, Amar
lei leis li duchtah l'meidar bei, no,
then I won't have anywhere to live. I don't know, he could
have said if you knock down one wall I won't have anywhere
to live during the time, but now—fine, I accept that you will
pay for the whole thing, I won't have anywhere to live. אמר
ליה אוגירנא לך דוכתא, Amar lei ogirna lach duchtah, I'll rent a
nice place for you. אמר ליה Amar lei לא טרחנא, lo tarachna.
I don't want to schlep my stuff there, I like where I
am right now. What?
Exactly. אמר רב חמא, Amar Rav Chama, so anyway, very similar to
the previous case, and again it's רב חמא Rav Chama who is
making—this is the description, before it was רב חמא, Rav Chama, here
it's רב חמא Rav Chama again, that's going to be important later.
אמר רב חמא בדין קא מעכב, Amar Rav Chama bedin ka me'akeiv,
you have a right to say that. I'm living in my house,
I don't have to do anything to accommodate you. You built a
building which
was unjustly
compromised my light, blocked out my light, you didn't have any right,
you know, you whatever transgressed that ordinance or the rule, it's your
responsibility to fix it, I don't have to do anything to make
my life easier for you. One minute, so the גמרא Gemara says
היינו הך, Hainu hach, isn't that essentially the previous thing? That that
the guy can claim look it's not my responsibility, you know, and
even if it's going to cost you a huge expense. So
the גמרא Gemara says והא תו למה לי, V'ha tu lamah li,
why do you need a second case? So the גמרא Gemara says
מהו דתימא Mahu d'teima to teach you that אף על גב דלא
משתמש אלא לתבנא וצבי דעלמא, af al gav d'lo mishtamesh ela l'tivna
v'tzivei d'alma, even if it wasn't even the house he was living
in, even if it was just my
storehouse for fodder and straw, I can still have that complaint there,
which that actually is a huge חידוש chiddush because you would say
how much do you need windows, you know, in a place that's
a storehouse for fodder? I mean I guess
you
still— But anyway, but that is obviously a bigger חידוש. chiddush.
David, you had a question about the language of בדין bedin כמאן?
keman? Is that... is there any ramification that is...
oh, you mean to say like the nice thing to do would
be is בדין bedin suggesting... I think בדין bedin here, it could
be read that way, בדין bedin as opposed to לפנים משורת הדין.
lifnim mishurat hadin. I understood it like, here he's making these claims,
are they legitimate claims or not? And the answer is those are
legitimate claims, you know? So you're right, you could have said מצי
מעכב, matzi me'akeiv, but I think it's like responding like, you know,
you're actually what you're saying is actually legally correct, you know? So,
all right,
so I didn't take anything from that. What? Solution?
You have to knock down your house and rebuild it far enough
away so that you're not blocking out my light. I mean, that's
what happens nowadays. I remember actually, I saw a show or whatever
somebody, somebody built a house and the roof, you know, was like
whatever it was, it was like two inches higher than the allowable
height. And they had to basically, you know, knock it down and
build it lower. So you know, if you're breaking, if you're violating
that ordinance, I'm sorry buddy, you know.
It was at my building they just built a new house next
to it and they put it right up smack against, they blocked
all those people's windows.
Well, yes, so it depends.
Right, it depends what the rules are, but building on the Upper
West...
on the East Side there was
a one that
goes that series of Trump buildings, so one of them was literally
against the next building next to it and there were big windows,
big signs on it: "Don't block our light."
Right, right, right. Yeah, it's a big thing. But if you're in
violation then it's your responsibility, whatever the expense, you mean you've got
to knock the whole thing down. Yeah.
There was a case in Maryland back in the 80s where they
had zoning for a two-story building and built a three-story building, had
to take off the upper, the top story.
Right, exactly. Okay.
When do they use בדין bedin
and when do they use הלכה? halacha?
Well, that's what David was asking. I don't think, I don't think
בדין bedin here, yeah, I think the word בדין bedin is just
a way of responding to the fact that it framed it as
somebody making these claims and they might seem like extreme claims because
you don't want to live in a hotel, I have to knock
down the whole thing, and nevertheless, it's saying you know what, they
are justified claims. So it's a way of, you know, it's not
a... it's not בדין bedin as a body of law, it's an
adjective as those are legitimate claims.
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So this is רב
חמא Rav Chama saying this all the time. Keep on going. הנו
בי תרי,
hanu bei
terei, so this is also really very interesting, there are two brothers
presumably, תרי אחי, tarei achi, oh, not presumably, דפלגי בהדי הדדי, defalgi
bahadi hadadi, they split the father's estate. חד מטא אספלידא, chad mata
asplida,
one took the אספלידא. asplida. רש"י Rashi says it means like a
mansion, like a beautiful building. תוספות Tosafot says it means actually like
a porticoed courtyard. Okay, we'll go with רש"י Rashi for now. וחד
מטא תרביצא, vechad mata tarbitza, and the other one took just the
open yard in front of the mansion. אזל ההוא
דמטא תרביצא, azal hahu demata tarbitza, the one who... seems like one
of them got a raw deal, we're going to see about that.
The one who took the yard went וקבנייה אשיטא אפומא דאספלידא, vekavneiya
ashita apuma de-asplida, and he started building a wall right in front
of the other guy's mansion. He was going "I got this yard,
fine, I'm going to build my house on this yard." אמר ליה
קא מפיחת עלי, amar lei ka mafchat alai, you're darkening things for
me. You can't do that. אמר ליה בדידי קבנינא, amar lei bedidi
kavenina, I'm building in my own space. Now of course, that's not
legitimate. You have to build far enough away so that you can
let the light in. So אמר רב חמא בדין קאמר ליה, amar
Rav Chama bedin ka-amar lei, actually that was a good response. Now
why was that a good response? You're not allowed to build so
close that you darken the guy's place. So now we're going to
find out why. But again, notice רב חמא Rav Chama is constantly
saying that phrase בדין קאמר ליה. bedin ka-amar lei. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, מאי שנא מהא דתניא, mai
shna me-ha detanya, how is this different from what we taught: שני
אחים שחלקו אחד מהם? shnei achim she-chalku echad me-hem? Now but I'll
stop here for a minute. Before we get to the technical challenge,
רש"י Rashi says it's possible here the reason that you have a
right to do it and even though you're causing the other place
to be dark is because you just recently split it up. So
nobody yet has established, in my mansion with those big windows, I
have not established my right to having the light. Okay? We just
split it
up yesterday and I'm going to start my construction right now. So
רש"י Rashi says it's an issue of the passage of time. You
know, which always gets to that question, am I compromising your use?
Have you established the right to have the use before...
exactly, so if you had this time point earlier in the...
exactly. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says בדידי
אנא בנינא, bedidi ana banina,
I don't know where that is, about 20 lines before the end.
בשלי אני בונה ואתה אין לך חזקת אורה. besheli ani boneh ve-ata
ein lecha chezkat orah. של שלוש שנים דהא שותפות גביהו. shel shalosh
shanim de-ha shutafut gabaihu.
Only after you've been have to have been living in this building
for three years and say I've have a I have the right
to have the type of light that I have in this building,
can you say I can't cut my light. So we haven't seen
that idea three years, we haven't seen the idea
but I understand that like cause he's protesting right away, if he
doesn't protest right, it doesn't fit the normal three-year thing, you know,
and we haven't seen this idea that like it's going to be
a good question, right? You do a barbecue in your yard, the
smoke comes into mine, can I sort of say, who gets to
say, well this is the way we've always done it, like what
makes you think you have a right for clean air? We both
have a right for a barbecue. Like how do you establish what's
the default, like who has the status quo right and who's being
compromised or not? So רשי Rashi introduces this idea three years, we
haven't seen that, you know, anyway that's the way רשי Rashi reads
it. Okay, so let's keep on going.
Is חזקת אורה chazkat orah is also like an astounding idea?
Well, why is that an astounding idea?
Exactly what we were talking about before, which is like do I
have a right to build my building on my property or do
you have a right to have the sunlight?
Right,
so in that story the issue of of time passing, the assumption
from that story was, I moved in yesterday and I have a
חזקת אורה. chazkat orah.
Wait, where, from which story? What are you talking about?
The story of the
I'll knock your house down.
No, one guy was you'd know, רשי Rashi understands that story, we've
been living nicely together for a while, for many years, I've been
having this light in my building for many years and you decided
to do a new construction project and to block my light. Here
we it was just recently divided. Alright let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes. מאי שנא mai shna
how is this different מהא דתניא שני אחים שחלקו אחד מהם נטל
שדה כרם ואחד נטל שדה לבן? me-ha de-tanya shnei achim she-chalaku echad
mehem natal sdeh karem ve-echad natal sdeh lavan?
They divided the fields, one person took the vineyards and the other
took the wheat field. יש לו לבעל הכרם ארבע אמות בשדה לבן.
yesh lo l-baal ha-karem arba amot b-sdeh lavan. So the person with
the vineyards you need ארבע אמות arba amot to to in order
to tend to the vines around the sides. So if you know,
if it's basically here's your vines, right, and here's your wheat field,
right, and we divided it as brothers right down there, that's technically
the wheat stops right there, nevertheless you can go ארבע אמות arba
amot within my yard in order to tend to your vines. Because
the standard amount of space needed to tend to the vines is
ארבע אמות. arba amot. So when we divide something, it's presumably it
gives everybody the presumed rights or the you know usage that they
would have in order to maintain you know that thing that they
got.
So without a wall, without a wall and so what about the
כלאים klayim issue?
Oh yeah that's a good question, maybe maybe I don't even have
wheat there but the line still is over there. Okay. So and
you get ארבע אמות. arba amot. So so
how's this different? You divided it so you should give me the
right to live in the house like I used to live like
we you know where it would normally be lived in and our
father lived in it with the light. בשדה לבן תמנא אסקן חילוק,
b-sdeh lavan tamna askan chiluk, אמר ליה amar lei התם דעלו להדדי
hatam de-alu le-hadadi אבל הכא מאי דלא עלו להדדי aval hacha mai
de-lo alu le-hadadi אבל תפרת דעלו להדדי aval tefert de-alu le-hadadi period.
Says
there no, cause there the case must be, assuming it's the same
acreage, the case must be that שמעון Shimon here, conveniently שמעון's Shimon
name is still there, that שמעון Shimon here got money עלו להדדי
alu le-hadadi means he got paid the difference of the value. Okay,
they made it up in cash. So assuming a grape field is
worth much more than a wheat field, assuming it's the same acreage,
so if ראובן Reuven got the better deal, presumably he paid שמעון
Shimon money for the difference. Once you're paying שמעון Shimon money for
the difference, it's assuming that that includes giving ראובן Reuven the normal
types of rights that he would need, the normal type of space
that he would need. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says but one
minute, in our case one guy got a mansion and one guy
got a yard, clearly there was a huge difference in price and
money was paid to make the difference. So the גמרא Gemara and
therefore again it should give the guy with the mansion his rights.
So the גמרא Gemara says אבל הכא מאי aval hacha mai in
our case what are you trying to say? דלא עלו להדדי de-lo
alu le-hadadi they did not pay money to pay for the difference?
וכי בשופטני עסקינן ve-chi b-shufatani askinan are we talking about idiots? דהאי
שקל אספלידא והאי שקל תרביצא de-hai shakal asplida ve-hai shakal tarbitza one
guy gets the mansion and one guy gets the yard ולא עלו
להדדי ve-lo alu le-hadadi and they didn't put up money in order
to pay for the difference make up for the difference? אמר ליה
amar lei so clearly they did and again we have the question
if I have this mansion I should be able to get the
light. אמר ליה amar lei נהי דעלו להדדי nehi de-alu le-hadadi no
maybe yes it is true they paid for the difference דמבני כשורי
והודרי de-mivne kishorei ve-hudrei in order for the cost of the bricks
and the various beams but the if we paid the difference it
was like okay a mansion is worth how much does it cost
to build a mansion with the building materials with everything, five million
dollars. I'm going to give you five million dollars, I got the
mansion you didn't get it. We also have the same amount of
acreage and property. I got it with the mansion you got it
without I'll give you five million dollars. So the גמרא Gemara What?
Oh, that's a good point. Thank you very much. I'll give you
two and a half million dollars. Okay fine. So they pay clearly
the difference they paid for was for the cost of the building
and the building materials and all of that, that's fine, they paid
for that difference.
David, I'm going to have you next time I go on a
to buy a house or something. Okay,
so, דהבו דמי
אוירא לא הלו אהדדי. da-havu d'mei avira lo halu ah-dadai. But you
know what they did not pay for the difference? They did not
pay for the difference for the air space, which רש״י Rashi says
means, hold on, let me just check רש״י, Rashi,
means that the guy basically says, where's, let me see if I
get this, yeah, like I've got the, I'm trying to see if
I can get this right. You got the mansion,
no, maybe it's different acreages is the point. Okay, you got the
mansion, okay, that's, I don't know why I do it like that.
I got the yard. Okay, so I got, you paid me for
the, you know, for the, for the value of the mansion. But
that did not pay me for, that was still assuming, I guess
it's saying that was still assuming that I had the rights to
use my property as I would see fit, right? I mean, I
guess that makes sense. If you're giving me the money that your
mansion costs, what am I going to do with the money? I'm
presumably going to build a house on my yard, right? Why was
I willing to take the yard and give you the mansion? Because
I'm planning on using that plot for building my own house, and
you're just paying me half of the cost of the mansion. So
I never sacrificed my right to use the, the air space, okay,
I was going to build on that air space.
But he didn't pay you for the air space.
He didn't buy that air space. Exactly. So therefore, even though you
paid me so I gave up my rights in the mansion, you
never paid me to give up my rights in using this acreage
to build my own house. Okay, so therefore it does not make
up for that difference. All right, so I still have rights to
use it to build my house. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולימא
ליה, v'leima leh, now why not say to him, מעיקרא אפלדא פלגית
לי, השתא משוית ליה
אדרונא? me-ikara apalida palgit li, hashta m'shavit leh idrona? No, but originally
when I agreed to take it, I agreed to take a palace.
A palace has nice big windows or whatever. Now you've turned it
into like an inner chamber, you've turned it into a, you know,
a tomb. Okay, it's totally dark. So that means that that wasn't
the deal I agreed to either. You wanted to have a plot
of land where you could build, I wanted a place that has
nice, you know, building with windows and light. So that wasn't, I
wouldn't, I implicitly I would never agree to this, yes?
Wouldn't he say I bought it under the assumption with the rule
of you can't build something close to me?
Right, like maybe you could build but not build right up against
me, right.
And wouldn't you normally buy air space from the other neighbor in
order to get the view if we have a standard rule that
you can't block someone's view, right?
Right, although right,
once that that rule has been established. I mean but I guess
what שמעון Shimon is saying is, no, but to make it fair
the assumption was I was going to take the money you gave
me and we both have equal types of, assuming anyway that this
is totally covering up its acreage and doesn't have a yard, the
entire yard is here, so I assumed that I was going to
get the equivalent. You were going to give me the money and
I was going to build the equivalent, you know, so. But then
he's saying but then I don't have, you know, assuming anyway this
is the best exposure, right, you could imagine that I'm going to
build here, I'm going to have my exposure with my light here.
I never build, I never paid that money, agreed to take a
tomb, I agreed to take a nice mansion. Okay let's take a
look. אמר רב שימי בר אשי, Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi, שמא
בעלמא פלגי ליה. shma b'alma palgei leh. No, I said I would
give you a mansion and it's still a mansion. Okay, it's a
dark mansion, but it's not like it compromised what we agreed upon.
מי לא תניא, mi lo tanya, do we not teach in a
ברייתא, Beraita, האומר בית כור עפר אני מוכר לך אף על פי
שאינו אלא לתך הרי זה. ha-omer beis kor afar ani mocher lach
af al pi she-eino ela lesech hiye.
So if I say I'm selling you an acre worth of property
and then I sell it to you and it's only a half
acre, a quarter acre, I can say yeah but that's the name
I give to my property, I call it acre. So like I
said I'm selling you an acre. So now it says that's legitimate,
שלא מכר לו אלא שם, shelo machar lo ela shem, that
you said I'm selling you an acre and that's its name, הוא
דמיקרי בית כור. hu d'mikri beis kor. I can't decide now to
call it acre, but if it's been called acre until now, you
know, after עכו Akko I guess, then it was legitimate. And תוספות
Tosafos says give me a break. First of all, how much money
did the guy pay, right? So תוספות Tosafos says no, let's say
I sold you, I said I'm going to sell you an acre
for a thousand dollars, now let's say acre normally goes for like
five, for five thousand dollars. So the question is the following: can
I say wait,
wait, how's it, right, and therefore so you're very eager to do
the deal, but therefore I sell you a little plot of land
that's only a fifth the size and I say oh this is
called acre. So you're getting your money's worth, so I'm not cheating
you in terms of your money, but you're basically saying I thought
I was going to get a whole acre. If this is what
we mean, I want to back out of the deal, I want
my money back. So the answer is sorry you can't back out,
you know, this is the way תוספות Tosafos frames it. You got
your money's worth and technically that was called acre, that was its
name. Yeah, Iceland is greener than Greenland. Anyway. So they named it
on purpose. Exactly. Yeah,
exactly. That's why I always go around and name all my half-acres
Acres just for fun. So it goes like this. פרדס אני מוכר
לך, Pardes ani mocher lach,
let's say you say I'm selling you a garden, אף על פי,
af al pi, like an orchard, excuse me, שאין בו רימונים, שאין
בו רימונים, even though there are no pomegranates, I guess פרדס רימונים
Pardes Rimonim assumes that a פרדס Pardes has pomegranates. הגיע, Higia, that's
still a legitimate sale, שלא מכר לו לשמא, she-lo machar lo l'shema,
that it's still called an orchard, והוא דמתקרי פרדס, v'hu d'miskari Pardes,
as long as it's still called an orchard. כרם אני מוכר לך,
Kerem ani mocher lach, I'm selling you a vineyard, אף על פי
שאין בו גפנים, af al pi she-ein bo gefanim, even if it
has no vines, you know, it had been a vineyard a while
ago, הגיע שלא מכר לו לשמא והוא דמתקרי כרם. Higia she-lo machar
lo l'shema v'hu d'miskari Kerem. Now again, it says in all these
cases, it has to be you're getting your money's worth. If you're
not getting your money's worth, then it's obviously voided. But
with
getting your money's worth, can you still say this wasn't what I
was expecting or not? And it says as long as that's still
the name, it's still good. It's a very bizarre הלכה, Halacha, I
know.
But if it used to be a vineyard, then you could plant
it. What if the soil isn't good?
Right, so I guess that would be a good question too. Is
it just arbitrarily? Let's say I say here's my dog, I call
my dog כרם. Kerem. Okay, like how much does it have to
be somewhat usable? Exactly. Anyway,
so
the point is that you're saying you're selling me a chamber, and
I'm saying it's still called a mansion. What do you want from
me? So the גמרא Gemara says no, מי דמי? mi dami? התם
מצי אמר ליה מוחל לוקח שמא זביני לך. Hatam matzi amar leh
mochal lokeh shema zevini lach. There, I sold you something called X
and this is called X. הכא מצי אמר ליה אדעתא דפג דדיורנא
בה כדמהוה התם. Hacha matzi amar leh ada'ata d'pag d'diurna beh ka-de-hava
hatam.
No, because here you could say it's not like there was a
sale and I said sell me a mansion. It's basically we all
knew what we were talking about and I said I would take
this part of the estate and it was understood and I would
continue to use it like it was used when our father was
alive, you know, with nice good sunlight. So it's not about labeling
something and selling something. We split. You take this, I take this,
and there was an assumption to be continued to be used as
normal. אמרו ליה, Amru leh, they said to him, מר ינוקא ומר
קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי. Mar Yanuqa u-Mar Kashisha brei de-Rav
Chisda le-Rav Ashi. So now again, remember רב חמא Rav Chama said
that you have a right to go ahead and build even though
you're darkening it. And now the גמרא Gemara is pushing back. So
we still don't have a resolution why רב חמא Rav Chama would
say you have that
right. So אמרו ליה מר ינוקא ומר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב
אשי, amru leh Mar Yanuqa u-Mar Kashisha brei de-Rav Chisda le-Rav Ashi,
נהרדעי טעמייהו. Naharda'ei ta'amayu. This רב חמא Rav Chama is from נהרדעא
Naharda and he goes according to the general position of those נהרדעי.
Naharda'ei. Of course שמואל Shmuel is from נהרדעא. Naharda. What does שמואל
Shmuel say?
דאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל האחים שחלקו אין להם לא דרך זה
על זה ולא חלונות זה על זה. D'amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel
ha-achim she-chilku ein lahem lo derech zeh al zeh v'lo chalonot zeh
al zeh. So let's say we split an estate.
Okay, here's our nice big plot of land. Here's the רשות הרבים.
reshut ha-rabim.
שמעון Shimon agrees to take the back one, ראובן Reuven agrees to
take the top. שמעון Shimon can't say to ראובן, Reuven, I have
a right to go through your property to get to mine. Nope,
we never agreed to that. We said I take this half, you
take that half. Okay, so you don't have any right to go
through my property. How are you going to do it? It's not
my problem. Go ahead and get yourself some wings to fly in,
but it's not my responsibility. Okay. This also there's related to a
question about the גמרא Gemara we're going to see later on, מוכר
בעין יפה הוא מוכר mocher b'ayin yafa hu mocher or בעין רעה
הוא מוכר. b'ayin ra'ah hu mocher. Do we assume a more generous
giving when things are transferred or a more stingy one? Anyway, האחים
שחלקו אין להם לא דרך זה על זה, ha-achim she-chilku ein lahem
lo derech zeh al zeh, they don't have rights of passage, ולא
חלונות זה על זה, v'lo chalonot zeh al zeh, and not rights.
רש"י Rashi says it means, you know, to say hey, you know,
I had the right to get light through my window. Nope, I'm
building in my own property. ולא סולמות זה על זה v'lo sulamot
zeh al zeh or to put ladders. If I get the top
part of a house and you get the bottom, I can't say
I have a right to lean my ladder against your house.
Nope, you took the upper part, but I didn't give you the
right to use my bottom part to lean your ladder. You'll have
to figure that out yourself. ולא אמת המים זה על זה v'lo
amat ha-mayim zeh al zeh and let's say there is a we
split a field and this רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim is actually where
there's an irrigation canal, then I don't have basically שמעון Shimon doesn't
have rights to get access to that irrigation canal, he doesn't have
rights through ראובן's Reuven's property. Okay. והזהרו בהן, V'hizharu ba-hen,
be careful about these laws, שהלכות קבועות הן, she-halachot kevu'ot hen, that
these are like fixed laws. Meaning yes, it sounds very unfair, but
if you know the laws you're playing with, then when you go
to split an estate, you know, as long as everybody knows the
rules of the game, that might be what the והזהרו v'hizharu is.
Then if you're getting this thing, you explicitly stipulate that you get
the right of passage and so on. Okay. So know what those
laws are because those are the laws. You get what you get
and you don't get upset. Okay. רבא אמר יש להם Rava amar
yesh lahem and רבא Rava says no, you do have some of
those normal types. types of usage rights. So here too, like the
right to light is a usage type of a right and רב
חמא Rav Chama says sorry, you don't get it. All right, if
people can give me two more minutes, I just want to get
to the משנה. Mishna. Okay,
ההוא שטרא
דיתמי דנפיק עליה תברא. Hahu shtara d'yasmi d'nafik alei tafra. So orphans
had a שטרא, shtar, meaning it said that somebody owed their father
a thousand dollars. Okay, and then this person, they're still like minor
orphans, and then this person produced an IOU. So אמר רב חמא,
Amar Rav Chama, אגבויי לא מגבינן ליה, agvuyei lo magvinan lei, we
don't collect the for the thousand dollars with the שטרא shtar because
there's an IOU, ומקרע לא קרעינן ליה, u'mikra lo karinan lei, but
we also don't throw out the שטרא. shtar. Why? Seems dangerous, leaving
a שטרא shtar that's been paid off. אגבויי לא מגבינן ליה, Agvuyei
lo magvinan lei, we don't collect it, דנפיק תברא ליה, d'nafik tafra
lei, that there's an I... that there's a receipt against it. I
said IOU, I meant receipt. Did I say IOU? Okay, anyway, there's
a receipt against it. Okay, so that's נפיק עליה תברא. nafik alei
tafra. תברא, Tafra, something that breaks it. There's a receipt against it.
Okay, so we don't collect it because there's a receipt against it,
דנפיק תברא ליה. d'nafik tafra lei. ומקרע לא קרעינן ליה, Mikra lo
karinan lei, we don't rip it up, דכי גדלי יתמי, d'chi gadli
yasmi, because then when they get older and they can look into
their father's finances and records, דילמא מייתי ראיה ומרעי ליה, dilma maisi
ra'aya u'marlei, maybe they'll find some evidence or maybe not just look
through the records, they'll ask around about it, they'll defend their own
interests and they'll find some evidence that this receipt is a bogus
receipt. Okay, so therefore we don't, you know, even though the evidence
seems like it's been paid and you have a legitimately signed and
sealed receipt.
Right, so I'm sorry if I used the term IOU and it
confused everyone. The orphans, the minor orphans are trying or whoever's their
appointed representative is trying to collect money owed to the father. Okay,
somebody owes the father a thousand dollars. Now this ראובן Reuven who
owed the father a thousand dollars has a receipt, not an IOU,
a receipt that says he paid it. Okay, so do we just
say fine, he paid it, tear up the שטרא. shtar. No, we
don't do that. Why do we not do that? We also obviously
don't let them collect if there's a receipt. But we don't tear
up the שטרא shtar because maybe when they get to be adults
and representing their own interests, they'll find a way to say that
the receipt was forged. Okay, and we leave them that option. Now,
the question is would we actually leave that as an open possibility?
So, דילמא מייתי ראיה ומרעי ליה. dilma maisi ra'aya u'marlei. אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרב לרבינא, Amlei Rav Acha brei d'Rav l'Ravina, הלכתא
מאי, hilchasa mai, do we פסקן pasken this way? So אמר ליה,
amlei, I'm sorry, did I skip a line? I skip... no, that
was... yeah, that was all רב חמא. Rav Chama. Notice all these
things are פסקים psakim of רב חמא. Rav Chama. So רב חמא
Rav Chama said בדין אמר ליה bedin amar lei when the guy
refused to move out of his house, you know, even if you're
going to pay to put me up in a hotel and you
know and do all those things, I you can't force me to
move. He said בדין אמר ליה bedin amar lei if I can
I can build a house even though it causes your place to
be dark when we're brothers that split. Normally I can't block your
light, but in that case I could. And here he says you
keep the you keep the שטרא shtar with the orphans. So he
says how do we פסקן pasken about all these things? Too bad
Michael isn't here because now the גמרא Gemara looks at the whole
previous דף daf and says נו, nu, what's the פסק? psak? So
the גמרא Gemara says הלכתא מאי, hilchasa mai, אמר ליה בכולהו הלכתא
כרב חמא, amlei bekulu hilchasa k'Rav Chama, we פסקן pasken like רב
חמא Rav Chama לבר מתברא, l'bar mi'tafra, except for the issue of
the receipt. So we פסקן pasken that you don't... you can't force
a guy out of his house even if, you know, it's causing
you all these troubles, even if you're offering to put him up
somewhere. If the brothers split, the other brother can build a building
even if it blocks the light. We פסקן pasken like רב חמא
Rav Chama but not in this case. This case we tear up
the שטרא. shtar. דסהדי בשקרי לא מחזקינן, D'sadi b'shikri lo machzinan, we
don't want to assume that the people who signed the receipt were
forged. You know, we don't assume that a document with signatures is
a forged document. מר זוטרא בריה דרב מרי Mar Zutra brei d'Rav
Mari אמר amar no, בהני נמי הלכתא כרב חמא. bahana nami hilchasa
k'Rav Chama. No, actually we do פסקן pasken like רב חמא Rav
Chama even in that case. We let them keep the שטרא, shtar,
maybe they'll prove that the... that the receipt is a forgery. דאם
איתא דתברא מעליא הוא D'im issa d'tavra ma'alya hu because there's a
little bit of a reason to suspect something is fishy. דאם איתא
דתברא מעליא הוא D'im issa d'tavra ma'alya hu if it really was
a legitimate receipt, איבעי ליה לאפוקי בחיי אבוהון. ibayei lei l'afukei b'chayei
avuhon. Why did we only start seeing it now that the father
is dead? Okay, ומדלא אפקיה שמע מינה זיופי זייפין u'med'lo afka shma
mina ziufei zeifin and since it only now appearing now, then there's
reason to think that maybe actually it is forged. So in all
these cases we will פסקן pasken like רב חמא. Rav Chama. Okay,
we can continue. Is it ironic that רב חמא Rav Chama is
the one...